<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>zero inflation on Lucio Palazzo</title>
    <link>https://blog-neas.github.io/it/tags/zero-inflation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in zero inflation on Lucio Palazzo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Lucio Palazzo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog-neas.github.io/it/tags/zero-inflation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Searching for the determinants of new social enterprises: the case of Italian social start-ups</title>
      <link>https://blog-neas.github.io/it/publications/determinants-siavs-ijas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog-neas.github.io/it/publications/determinants-siavs-ijas/</guid>
      <description>Social start-ups constitute a subclass of the innovative entrepreneurship market and they are a relatively new topic in the literature from both the scientific and normative perspectives. In Italy, a start-up can be registered as social-oriented innovative startup (SIAVS), after demonstrating its ability to make social impacts and satisfy a set of normative requirements. This paper describes and models (at the territorial level) the presence of these innovative companies focused on social, cultural, and/or environmental needs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Determinants of social startups in Italy</title>
      <link>https://blog-neas.github.io/it/publications/asa21-bosp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog-neas.github.io/it/publications/asa21-bosp/</guid>
      <description>Nota: L&amp;rsquo;articolo originale è in lingua inglese. Di seguito viene presentata una traduzione dell&amp;rsquo;abstract.
Lo scopo di questo articolo è quello di indagare i fattori rilevanti che influenzano la presenza di startup sociali in Italia a livello provinciale. La variabile di risultato è il numero di startup sociali attive nelle province italiane mentre il set di variabili esplicative è composto da indicatori economici e demografici a livello provinciale.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
