<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Network Analysis on Lucio Palazzo</title>
    <link>https://blog-neas.github.io/en/tags/network-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Network Analysis on Lucio Palazzo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Lucio Palazzo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog-neas.github.io/en/tags/network-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Local clustering coefficient to measure intra-regional tourism in Italy</title>
      <link>https://blog-neas.github.io/en/publications/ies22-idea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog-neas.github.io/en/publications/ies22-idea/</guid>
      <description>Network analysis represents a useful approach to measure intra-regional tourism flows. Relevant information about this phenomenon can be retrieved using Network Analysis local clustering coefficient (LCC). In this work we study Italian tourism flows in two-year period 2018-2019, identifying different patterns and two main groups of regions. This preliminary study shows the potential of LCCs to evaluate the effects of tourism policies in terms of attractiveness and receptivity of a region (or groups of regions).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sviluppo della cultura statistica a scuola e all&#39;università: buone pratiche dal territorio</title>
      <link>https://blog-neas.github.io/en/publications/istat18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog-neas.github.io/en/publications/istat18/</guid>
      <description>TBA</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Corsi universitari campani e competenze professionali: un&#39;analisi relazionale</title>
      <link>https://blog-neas.github.io/en/publications/orsuc-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog-neas.github.io/en/publications/orsuc-book/</guid>
      <description>Note: The original chapter is written in Italian. Here you can find a translation of the abstract.
In this paper we identify the relationships between the Italian university courses and students&#39; first job categories. University courses in Italy are divided in bachelor (corsi di studio, CdS) and master degrees (corsi di laurea,CdL), while the professional sectors are categorized by the ATECO codes, officially introduced by the Italian institute of statistics (ISTAT).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
